Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
- Record Group 8. Alumni and alumni-relations (1891-2015; 28.5 linear feet), 216971; 28.5 Linear feet
  - Series III. Alumni materials, 1892-2013; 216975; 14.5 Linear feet
    - Subseries III.B. Alumni biographies, 1912-1999
      - Class of 1947 50th reunion publication, 1997 (Offsite-box 273, Folder 3)
        Alumni reunion newsletter in the style of Fieldston News.
      - Normal School alumni (2 folders), undated (Offsite-box 107, Folder 1-2)
        Two items on alumni. Book with list of graduates for each year.
      - World War II alumni correspondence (2 folders), 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 3-4)
        Letters from enlisted alumni to Luther Tate in response to the school's Christmas cards. Includes list of updates on alumni in military.
      - Yearbook excerpts (4 folders), 1929-1970 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 5-8)
        Pages on senior class.
    - Subseries III.C Mabel Towne Burnham, 1892-1970
      Mabel Towne Burnham, long-time Ethical Culture School employee, served in roles including Director of the Summer Play School in the 1920s, and Registrar in the 1930s. The series primarily contains scrapbooks she made during her years at Ethical Culture, along with clippings and ephemera intended for or removed from scrapbooks. It also includes some personal items (such as a diary and account books), and notebooks and printed matter from Essex High School and the Salem Normal School. The bulk of materials were created between 1900 and 1945.
      This subseries begins with materials collected by Burnham on the Ethical Culture Schools, followed by materials related to her own education.
      - Scrapbooks - "M.T.B." (3 folders), 1919-1922 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 1-3)
        One book for each academic year, with ephemera related to the Ethical Culture School, with some notes and photographs.
      - Scrapbooks - alumni (2 folders), 1952-1955 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 4-5)
        News clippings on Ethical Culture and Fieldston School alumni.
      - Scrapbook clippings (6 folders), 1906-1929 (Offsite-box 199, Folder 6-11)
        Clippings of correspondence, ephemera, and newspaper articles related to the Ethical Culture School.
      - Scrapbook clippings (13 folders), 1939-1947, 1953-1960 (Offsite-box 200, Folder 1-13)
      - Ethical Culture Society ephemera (3 folders), 1919-1947 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 1-3)
      - Fieldston ephemera, 1970, undated (Offsite-box 201, Folder 4)
      - Materials related to the Ethical Culture Schools (10 folders), 1901-1947 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 5-14)
        Teacher schedules, class lists, ephemera, curriculum materials, reports, and student work.
      - Notebooks (3 folders), 1905-1922 (Offsite-box 201, Folder 15-17)
        Diary 1907-1918, account book 1922, list of pupils, some other education-related notes.
      - Administrative notebooks - book and supply orders (3 folders), 1940-1957 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 1-3)
        Notes including entries on Salem Summer Shop supply orders and "household cash accounts." Also brochures on plays for children.
      - Essex High School ephemera, 1892-1941 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 4)
        Ephemera from Essex High School and the Essex alumni association. Some pencil drawings and photographs.
      - Essex High School and Salem Normal School student notebooks (11 folders), 1895-1905 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 5-15)
      - Miscellaneous student notebooks, 1892-1904 (Offsite-box 202, Folder 16)
        Notebooks used by Burnham or her pupils.
      - Salem Normal School ephemera (3 folders), 1897-1905 (Offsite-box 45, Folder 1-3)
        Booklets on various educational subjects, some with notes.
      - Salem Normal School - student publications, 1904, undated (Offsite-box 45, Folder 4)
      - Ephemera - other (4 folders), 1912-1938 (Offsite-box 45, Folder 5-8)
        Mostly materials related to education.
      - Duplicate print matter collected by Burnham, 1909-1964 (Offsite-box 203)
- Record Group 9. Development and communications (1885-2009; 17.25 linear feet), 216978; 17.25 Linear feet
  Record Group 9 consists of materials related to development and communications efforts for the Ethical Culture Fieldston School. Subject matter includes development appeals, the management of gifts and funds, school programs, public relations, and strategic planning.
  It contains a small amount of materials from the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, but the vast majority of records were created after the establishment a dedicated program for fund-raising and publicity in the 1950s. Types of materials include correspondence, reports, meeting materials, press releases, ephemera, and news clippings. Files related to the celebration and publicity of the school's various anniversary celebrations can also be found in this record group.
  Records related to fund-raising for the construction of new buildings, especially Tate Library, can be found in Record Group 10, Buildings and grounds. Administrative and Board of Governors materials in Record Group 1 also often involve development or public relations efforts.
  Series I: Fund-raising and publicity before 1950
  Series II: Fund-raising and publicity, 1950s-1970s
  Series III: Development and communications, 1980-2000s
  - Series I. Fund-raising and publicity before 1950, 1885-1949; 216980; 1 Linear feet
    This small series contains early fund-raising and publicity records, mostly related to the school's 60th Anniversary celebrations.
    This series is arranged in chronological order (imposed by the archivist).
    - Workingman's School appeals and benefits, 1885, undated (Offsite-box 107, Folder 9)
      Ephemera. Includes facsimiles of Ethical Culture Society "Building Fund" notebook and newspaper clipping.
    - 50th Anniversary, 1926 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 10)
      Pamphlet.
    - 60th Anniversary - planning materials, 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 11)
      Committee work, meeting materials, and Parent Teacher Association records.
    - 60th Anniversary - correspondence (7 folders), 1938-193 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 12-18)
      Correspondence of the administration, Parent and Teacher Association, alumni, vendors, and administrators and teachers at other schools. Topics include event planning, publicity, committee work, and the World's Fair film. Responses to invitations to the school's "birthday dinner" make up much of the files.
    - 60th Anniversary - alumni-related materials, undated (Offsite-box 107, Folder 19)
    - 60th Anniversary - articles and speech transcripts, 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 20)
      Also some ephemera and "scenario of film later shown at World's Fair - N.Y. - 1939."
    - 60th Anniversary - brochures and flyers, 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 21)
    - 60th Anniversary - lists, publicity plans, and history (2 folders), 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 22-23)
      Press releases, lists of notable alumni, "birthday dinner" materials, correspondence, and histories of the school.
    - 60th Anniversary - sponsors and school events, 1936-1938 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 24)
      Ephemera and list of sponsors, with correspondence accepting or declining.
    - Building fund - Fieldston Assembly Hall, 1945-1949 (Offsite-box 107, Folder 25)
      Correspondence, planning materials, lists.
  - Series II. Fund-raising and publicity, 1950s-1970s, 1950-1983; 216981; 12.25 Linear feet
    Series II contains records from the administrative office for fund-raising and publicity from the 1950s through the 1970s. This era saw the establishment of the Ethical Fieldston Fund and the Development Committee, with regular appeals to alumni and parents, and simultaneously, the creation of the Public Relations Working Committee and the publication of the 1954 report, "A Public Relations Program for the Ethical Culture Schools."
    Fund-raising materials include copies of appeals, committee and meeting materials, reports on campaigns and funds, and correspondence. Publicity efforts, often managed by the same staff, are represented in committee materials, correspondence, and a good deal of press releases, which were created frequently in this era. Background materials on various school programs, as well as some general school administrative records can also be found in this record group.
    Related records can be found in Record Group 1, Subseries IV.C., the records of the editorial and publicity assistant to Director Victoria Wagner.
    Subseries II.A: Ethical Fieldston Fund and appeals
    Subseries II.B: Projects, campaigns, and events
    Subseries II.C: Administrative and foundational records
    Subseries II.D: Public relations
    - Subseries II.A. Ethical Fieldston Fund and appeals, 1952-1980
      This subseries contains records related to the Ethical Fieldston Fund, and records of appeals to specific constituent groups, including alumni, parents, and grandparents.
      Files in this subseries are arranged by their original order.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund (3 folders), 1952-1962 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 1-3)
        Campaign materials and correspondence. Includes consultant's report "Capital Fund Raising Program," 1959.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - organization and personnel (5 folders), 1962-1969 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 4-8)
        Organization charts, job descriptions, timelines, memoranda, lists, and planning documents for various campaigns and committees.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - constitution and by-laws, 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 9)
        Also includes 509a3 letter and lists of officers.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund (4 folders), 1967-1972 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 10-13)
        Reports, correspondence, solicitor information, committee materials, and meeting minutes.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - Executive Committee (6 folders), 1970-1980 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 14-19)
        Meeting materials, correspondence, lists of members, and financial data, on topics including campaigns, foundation work, state of the fund, and events. Some correspondence relates to the publication of the Ethical Reporter and alumni directory.
      - Robert Schwartz (2 folders), 1971-1975 (Offsite-box 108, Folder 20-21)
        Correspondence of Schwartz, Chairman of the Ethical Fieldston fund.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - annual appeals (3 folders), 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 1-3)
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund contributors (2 folders), 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 4-5)
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - Board of Directors, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 109, Offsite-box 6)
        Includes 1975 Ethical Fieldston Fund Manual of Procedures.
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - annual appeals (4 folders), 1976-1979 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 7-10)
      - Ethical Fieldston Fund - theater benefit, 1976-1980 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 11)
        Also includes general fund-raising and planning materials.
      - Specific foundations (4 folders), 1957-1977 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 12-15)
        Correspondence and notes. Foundations organized alphabetically or by likelihood of giving.
      - Foundation appeals and information (5 folders), 1965-1973 (Offsite-box 109, Folder 16-20)
      - Foundation information (3 folders), 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 1-3)
      - Foundations, correspondence with (2 folders), 1977-1979 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 4-5)
      - Appeals - procedures and outlines, undated (Offsite-box 110, Folder 6)
      - Fund-raising appeals and notes, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 7)
      - Various appeals (8 folders), 1956-1976 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 8-15)
        Appeals, related to guidance and social work, arts, Tate Library, and other school programs.
      - Alumni appeals (3 folders), 1962-1975 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 16-18)
        Appeals to alumni and work with the Alumni Association.
      - Alumni - Middle Range Committee records (3 folders), 1968-1973 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 19-21)
      - Alumni - reunions (6 folders), 1965-1975 (Offsite-box 110, Folder 22-27)
        Correspondence, lists of alumni, and solicitations.
      - Class agent letters, 1968-1971 (Offsite-box 111, Folder 1-14)
        Correspondence, including solicitation letters, and lists of results.
      - Parents of graduates, 1958-1951 (Offsite-box 111, Folder 15-16)
        Includes list of parents - classes of 1915-1950.
      - Parents council, 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 1)
      - Parents of graduates - appeals (5 folders), 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 2-6)
        Includes records for the class agents, mass appeals, and the Parents VI Form Committee.
      - New parents (3 folders), 1967-1976 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 7-9)
      - Parents of graduates, 1969-1971, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 10)
      - Parents - middle and upper range (4 folders), 1967-1971 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 11-14)
      - Parents, 1971-1976 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 15)
        Includes materials on fund-raising and Parent and Teacher Association programs.
      - Grandparents (4 folders), 1963-1968 (Offsite-box 112, Folder 16-19)
        Lists of grandparents, correspondence, grandparent events.
      - Grandparents - appeals (3 folders), 1967-1975 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 1-3)
        Grandparents Committee work and appeals to grandparents.
      - Faculty appeals and contributions, 1960-1967 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 4)
      - Appeals by profession (2 folders), 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 5-6)
        Luncheons and other events for members of specific professions: lawyers, doctors, or individuals working in communications or finance.
      - College class solicitations, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 7)
        Appeals from current college students to their classmates.
    - Subseries II.B. Projects, campaigns, and events, 1951-1980
      This subseries contains records for various fund-raising campaigns and projects, as well as information on other school programs for fund-raising or publicity use.
      - Ephemera, 1951-1959 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 8)
        Ephemera, including for the 1951 "Emergency Campaign."
      - Development projects - various (2 folders), 1955-1970 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 9-10)
        Includes the gymnasium building fund and 3-School programs.
      - Background materials (2 folders), 1956-1968 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 11-12)
        Information on teacher training and tuition.
      - Art auctions (2 folders), 1959-1968 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 13-14)
        Ephemera, new clippings, and press releases and other publicity materials.
      - Art auction ephemera - oversize, 1968 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 8)
      - Endowments, 1961-1964 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 15)
      - Ethical school expansion, 1962-1962 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 16)
      - Fieldston tutorial program and summer school, 1964-1973 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 17)
      - Upward Bound (4 folders), 1965-1969 (Offsite-box 113, Folder 18-21)
        Program information, foundation and other fund-raising work, some publicity work and press clippings.
      - Tate Library forum and committee, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 1)
      - Large Gifts Committee (2 folders), 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 2-3)
      - Projects - various (7 folders), 1967-1978 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 4-10)
        Topics include Expo '71, Fieldston auditorium project, arts programs, the Second Century Fund, and the 1978 Gala.
      - Tate Library donor cards, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 317)
        Box in index cards, in alphabetical order, with names and addresses of donors. (Cards contain no information about amounts donated.)
      - General school information and miscellaneous (2 folders), 1970-1976 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 11-12)
      - School lists (2 folders), 1970-1973 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 13-14)
        Fund-raising lists such as solicitors and potential contributors, and registration lists such as new acceptances or college matriculations.
      - Benefits (4 folders), 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 15-18)
        Correspondence and planning documents for raffles, events, and performances.
    - Subseries II.C. Administrative and foundational records, 1951-1978
      This subseries consists of materials created on the history of fund-raising at the Ethical Culture Fieldston Schools, as well as administrative records from the fund-raising and publicity offices.
      - History of fund-raising (4 folders), circa 1950-1962 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 18-22)
        Materials compiled on the early history of fund-raising at the schools. Includes several lists, such as early donors to the Workingman's School or alumni contributions by year. Also includes records on the establishment of the Development Committee and reports on various fund-raising efforts during the 1950s.
      - Constitutions and by-laws (2 folders), 1951-1978 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 23-24)
        For the Ethical Culture Schools and the Ethical Fieldston Fund.
      - Personnel practices, 1957, 1961 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 25)
      - Regulatory matters, 1962-1975 (Offsite-box 114, Folder 26)
        Materials related to government regulation and tax exemptions.
      - Administrative supplies and vendors (7 folders), 1965-1977 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 1-7)
        Invoices, purchase requisitions, receipts, and correspondence related to office supplies, postage, materials for stationery and brochure printers, and other vendor services and products.
      - Accounts and daily reports (2 folders), 1966-1977 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 8-9)
      - Administration and faculty (2 folders), 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 10-11)
        Correspondence and meeting minutes.
    - Subseries II.D. Public relations, 1950-1983
      This subseries contains records related to the planning and execution of public relations programs.
      This subseries is arranged in chronological order, followed by materials related to the observance of school anniversaries, and by press releases.
      - Report: A Public Relations Program for the Ethical Culture Schools (2 folders), 1954-1958 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 12-13)
        Copies of 1954 report by Rosalie Slocum, with progress report updates.
      - Public Relations Working Committee (2 folders), 1954-1963 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 14-15)
        Minutes, planning documents, some correspondence, lists of members. Also copy of "Administrative procedures for special projects operated by the Ethical Culture Schools, " 1956.
      - Background materials for campaigns (7 folders), 1954-1959 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 16-22)
        Folders (original titles): Faculty - cailiber of, ECS influence on public education, Research programs - the search for new truths, Outstanding characteristics of ECS program, Students - caliber of and college record, Alumni - caliber of, and Scholarship program.
      - Committees, 1955-1958 (Offsite-box 115, Folder 23)
        Guidelines and procedures, meeting materials, lists of members, and memoranda for the Publications Committee, and the Information Committee (renamed as the News and Research Committee in 1956).
      - Parents Council and Parent and Teacher Association, 1957-1972 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 1)
      - Clippings and publications, 1959, 1965, undated (Offsite-box 116, Folder 2)
      - Teaching and Learning, 1962-1973 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 3)
      - Various projects (4 folders), 1964-1976 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 4-8)
        Materials relating to a scholarship program report, brochure production, the "Sunshine '73" event, and establishment of a book award.
      - Archives inquiry - Lewis Hine, 1967-1983 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 9)
      - Publicity (2 folders), 1971-1977 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 10)
      - Anniversaries (5 folders), 1950- 1983 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 11-15)
        Press releases, plans, news clippings, correspondence, ephemera, and other materials related to the Ethical Culture School's 75th, 85th, and 100th anniversary celebrations, and the Fieldston Lower 50th anniversary.
      - Press releases (5 folders), 1961-1966 (Offsite-box 116, Folder 16-20)
        Press releases throughout this series typically publicize student and faculty achievements, new hires, school athletics, performances and exhibitions, and other events. Often press releases are intended for specific local publications.
      - Press releases (11 folders), 1966-1972 (Offsite-box 117, Folder 1-11)
      - Press releases (2 folders), 1970-1983 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 1-2)
        1977-1979 files also contain some correspondence.
      - News clipping scrapbooks (MISSING Oct 2019), 1955-1969 (Offsite-box 122)
        Two scrapbooks with newspaper clippings of press related to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School. Includes articles on the school and its programs, and student and staff achievements, as well as clippings of paid advertisements for the school.
      - Clippings scrapbooks (MISSING Oct 2019), 1964-1979 (Offsite-box 123)
      - Clippings scrapbooks (2 books), 1970-1991 (Offsite-box 266)
  - Series III. Development and communications, 1980s-2000s, 1977-2009; 216982; 4 Linear feet
    This series consists of records from the development and communications offices. In addition to specific fund-raising campaigns, it contains records related to long-term strategic planning and branding of the schools. Types of materials include meeting materials, correspondence (often printed emails, in later records), memorandum, reports, ephemera, notes, news clippings.
    This series is arranged in alphabetical order (imposed by the archivist).
    - 125th Anniversary, 2004 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 3)
    - Accreditation and by-laws, 1984 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 4)
    - Administrative, 1991-1992, undated (Offsite-box 118, Folder 5)
    - Alumni, 2004-2005 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 6)
    - Board of Trustees, 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 7)
    - Building projects (4 folders), 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 8-11)
      Communications, development, and environmental sustainability materials.
    - Campaigns and appeals (3 folders), 1977-2003 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 12-14)
    - Capital Campaign Planning Committee, 1978-1980s (Offsite-box 119, Folder 1)
      Background materials and meeting minutes for 1984 project.
    - Capital Campaign feasibility study, 1993 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 2)
    - ECS Reporter - draft copies and galleys, 1981-1992, 2006 (Offsite-box 273, Folder 1)
      Editorial drafts of the ECS Reporter demonstrating changes in formatting and word processing procedures. Also with 2006 letter on donation of copies.
    - Ethical Fieldston Endowment Campaign, 1984-1989 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 3-4)
      Meeting minutes and ephemera.
    - Ethical Fieldston Fund (6 folders), 1980-2000 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 5-10)
      Annual appeals and auctions.
    - Foundations (2 folders), 1980-1981, 1991 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 11-12)
    - Funds - endowed and named (2 folders), 1991-2001 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 13-14)
    - Grandparents (2 folders), 1979-1993 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 15-16)
      Mostly Grandparents Day materials.
    - Long-range plan report, 1977-1987 (Offsite-box 119, Folder 17)
    - Major gifts (3 folders), 1993-1994 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 1-3)
      Records of the Major Gifts Committee, and major gift assignments.
    - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1985-2009 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 4)
    - New York State Association of Independent Schools (4 folders), 1990-1997 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 5-8)
      Regarding development planning, school evaluations, and regulations.
    - Office for Institutional Advancement and Alumni, 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 9)
    - Other schools, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 10)
    - Photo archive, 1987-1990 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 11)
    - Proposals, 1993-2000 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 12)